open dedicating with John verb a key on
the cognitive psychologist and a
cognitive scientists at the University
of Toronto academic engage in scientific
study mindfulness and related phenomena
like insight flow mystical experience
higher states of consciousness
formative experience cultivation of
wisdom in the aspiration light and touch
each come as an integrated a dynamic
quality practices for over twenty nine
years teaching them professionally for
close to 20 years welcome
if you're joining us this is a
progressive course in the introductory
course is done I suggest you do is in
the description for this video go to
links for lesson 1 we get the watch
lesson 1 do it and then every Saturday
or Sunday work your way through the
lessons and that way you can catch up as
you attend this Sangha we need every day
Monday every week there should say
Monday to Friday at 9:30 Mondays
alternate between one Monday is a Dharma
day and which radiation and principle of
practice and the next Monday is a Friday
in which I go over the entire ecology in
one session so they can get a sense of
how it looks when it's all fitted
together so probably need to do to help
me out please
please like this video stream it'll help
raise its presence on the youtube search
algorithm and that will help you reach
as many people as possible reminder that
at the end of every session we have
together there is a Q&A but please keep
the q and a's for those sessions to the
questions concerning this course the
psychology of practice for more
encompassing questions please come to my
livestream general Q&A every third
Friday on YouTube at 3 p.m. and B third
Friday a month and first one I'm sort of
the one person on the first one the one
for this month for
is June 19 and that's where you can ask
you know very encompassing broad
questions I think that's everything and
so as promised I'd like to go over
review what was taught on Monday and
then there was a little bit of extension
of it on Wednesday and it'll be a little
bit added to it again today so review of
that just a little bit more and then
we'll have sort of a core Chi cung
practice we can build on forward okay so
yeah another term sign-on to remind you
how to get a little G okay so you want
your feet about shoulder-width apart you
don't want your toes turned out so if I
don't want my feet on an angle like this
right I want my feet straight forward
and I want them to be like a bend in my
knees a I do that as I put my hands out
I make sure my elbows aren't rolled up
but down like there's weights on them
and then as if I'm going to sit down I
tell my coccyx in to bend my knees and
then I open my hands and let my arms
drop beside and there's like the eggs in
my armpits
so that's wushi that's a way of deeply
activating and integrating mind of body
into a stable rooted dynamic sensitivity
okay so we're in Fuji and then we're
going to do embracing the treatment of
the Jeong Jeong exercise bring your
hands up right and it's like you're
bracing a big treat so my hands below my
shoulders my elbows below my wrists
about a hand width apart as I kind of
squeezing a big ball this way big spongy
ball this way and this way squeezing a
ball between my legs and I'm also
squeezing as I sit down and then you do
four we'll just do four baby breaths
here as you do in meditation
remember Center yourself you're not on
your heels you're not on your toes
you're not on your right and on your
left foot okay now the beginning of each
one exercises
inhaling and again spongy ball exhaling
remember you're still sitting on your
spongy ball and squeezing it between
your knees mount fire in the belly
brings your hands in come here
I'm sure spit your muscle breathing in
feeling that heat between your hands
right into the ducts of your dunk energy
breath for breaths again
still sitting on your ball
and the microcosmic orbit old men
stroking his beard and Barresi inhale
heat that clinched he got all the
way up to the top of her head and down
central on your face back to where you
started
reciprocal opening so I've got ten then
move to your heart opening the heart
opening centrical opening of mine Sifl
opening with the world in each case
super cool opening of the spirit sense
of self transcendence
now the oo-ahh pull up your head first
[Music]
now you have your mind your head your
intellect area
[Music]
art
don't ya
and slightly sign on if you leave got a
week better orientation for wheeling
this silk so let's just get the physical
going first today we're going to add in
a mental component to really know so so
now any shift my weight and remember I'm
moving here but I move my hips from my
don t N and heart and head just come
along from the ride I'm not moving from
my head downward I'm not turning my head
and dragging my body I'm moving upward
from the earth I turn my hips my mind is
in my don t and that's where the center
my agency is I turn my hips I turn my
hips and that turns my heart and my head
I don't fold my knees in and I don't
move my toes sole across here scooping
here here so this is an inhale and then
this goes down this comes up exhale
inhale to the left exhale to the right
wheeling silk remember just enough
tension that you would reel this up but
not too much they would snap it inhaling
to the law turn your hips to turn your
heart and your head off from the earth
walk down from your head
okay now we're going to add a final
component for this the mental component
so what you're going to do is you're
going to be as you do an in-breath and
an out breath you're going to alternate
between sort of doing something like
making something happen with your mind
sort of doing and that's the end and
then feel it that's the end so first
what I'm going to do although there's a
yin component to this what I'm doing is
I'm softening I'm trying to soften my
mind and my body so go to my left
softening and then to my right song for
me okay now when I go to the left my
second time what is what can I feel
because I've softened I want to feel
suppleness like a young sapling and when
I feel something us so let's start again
let's go like soften okay so to the left
and soften then I feel suppleness
Hey what's the next one I'm gonna do
each one of these pairs and then we'll
do them all together the next is
smoothing so what the smoothing means
I'm trying to smooth the transitions of
mind and body so mine isn't jerking and
my body isn't jerky
I'm trying to smooth my mind in my body
okay
so let's for we will do the softening
first again soften and soften and then
feel suppleness like a young sapling
okay now smooth smooth the transitions
of mind and body okay what are you
feeling as a result of smoothy you're
feeling subtlety your feelings how
things are subtle you're trying to have
smoothness by that smoothing allows you
to pick up on very subtle movements of
you know awareness and energy in your
body okay so let's do it again we're
going to start going to do softening
right and that's okay you know pluck you
through it okay so going to the life
softening soften now feel suppleness
supplements okay now smoothing
now you fill that subtleness subtleness
of oceans of mind and body so you got
suppleness and suppleness or subtlety I
guess okay so the important thing when
you're doing this is to try and sense
how each one of these is affording the
next okay so we've done softening for
suppleness then smoothing for some of us
next one let me explain - but you're
gonna be diffusing what that means is
because he's got everything doing like
this you're trying to suffuse the whole
of your body with your mind so you try
to feel your like aliveness and
communication awareness throughout the
whole of your body you want the whole of
your body in your mind so that what's
filling your mind and there's nothing
else in there is your body okay and so
you're just refusing
okay so let's again soften okay and then
we're going to detect some subtleness
some suppleness now smoothing
now it supplements some system where
that's our so the softening is bringing
the suppleness the smoothing is bringing
that awareness of subtle motions of mind
and body awareness and energy now now
we're going to do stuff using diffusing
mind and body
what are we feeling
well it's shiny not in the sense of
light although the vitamin E helps the
word phenomena grief actually means how
things shine with what's good here is a
sense of how everything is present
shining like when we talked about the
lecture convenient all of your body and
all of the world around you everything
is for singing its name okay so let's
build towards this again so softening
suppleness
smoothing subtlety
now suffusing shine
okay so the last one or at least last
one is sinking but it's good in your
mind to think of stone sinking sy and C
because it's both sinking and getting
everything instinct and here's what you
gonna try and this is like a basic
control with weight underside you're
gonna try to feel everything sinking and
most importantly your mind and your
energy sitting not dropping like when
you're exhausted but sinking into a
little root a root all the way through
your body
everything is sinking and everything is
getting in sync
okay so let's skip there again softening
smooth sort of subtlety suppleness
that's starting it I apologize let's
start again soften suppleness smoothing
subtlety
suffusing shiny now sinking my body into
instinct completely insane every
molecule in sync with every other
molecule over your body and what are you
feeling here you're feeling how
self-organizing you're not doing it it's
taking on a life of its own working its
way out like music like when you're
listening to music and interesting and
how much your body and you start to move
with the rhythm and then you can slow it
down
okay so let's review
alright always an in-breath for the lab
right I'm softening and then I'm feeling
suppleness like a young sapling I'm
smoothing the transitions of mind and
body so I can feel supple motions from
several events like fine detail and I'm
just refusing filling body with mine and
by my mind with body and I'm feeling
about everything is shiny and finally
sinking sinking and getting instinct so
you can feel how everything is
self-organizing oh this is like music
rhythm that i'm inhabiting and it's
inhabiting me and it's working its way
playing its way out through me Tai Chi
Chuan they're a cheap player but you're
playing music your body is a musical
instrument and you're also like
listening to that one of the same time
ok let's do the final thing just
bringing down the heavens on the front
down the back through the core all three
at once and then back into wuji good but
sit well if we're all I'm going to sit
for ten minutes today so that we can
have some time for some questions I'll
also put in the notes to this video that
sequence what you're doing with your
mind all right while you're doing
milling the silk doing feeling really
feeling doing feeling doing through them
okay
all right so let's get ready and posture
please set your phones to do not disturb
and we will begin together when I say
yet again
but you cultivated in your practice with
your everyday consciousness and
cognition crops by reciting the five
precepts the five promises to yourself
okay we'd have time for a couple
questions as I said I'll put in some
notes for the way you layer the mental
on top of the physical movements in
willingness ilk I think you're also
noticing my practices get a layer on to
each other in in ecology practices you
want practices that complimentary
relationships to each other
complimentary sets the strengths and
weaknesses you want to have practices
and that they layer on each other and
then you want to have practices that
link other practices to each other so
Brett has a question pleasure though
Monday night we participated in a zoom
ecstatic dance party that sounds
wonderful
I assume this is on the discord server I
found it pretty meditative focusing on
my movements any other tips for turning
dance into a meditation yeah I'm going
to show you a practice part of the
psychology drawn from Tantra that
basically integrate something like dance
and she come on together so that's
coming I found on the road not that long
from now
karema yesterday when you you're using
egos voice and what does this mean the
only way to connect the only to connect
to the world is depressed but the only
way to connect to the mind body is to
transmit so when the ego is talking that
way what it's claiming is that the only
way like that I can be connected to the
world is right my way I can be connected
to the world that is to grasp it to take
hold of it
right and then what you're realizing and
the same with the body the body is like
I own my body i bided wrap grasp it
possession of it but that is not the
only way for the connectedness to be
think about what I was trying to get you
to realize and both senses of the word
realized when we're doing willingness
ilk you're not
spin your body it's and it's not even
like I know the verb is you're playing
but it's like the way you when you play
music right you're not grasping music
holding onto it you're conforming
yourself can in a continuity contact of
how it's continually transforming and it
is inhabiting you and you are inhabiting
it it's a reciprocal continuity of
ongoing flowing transformation mutuality
like a mutuality of transformation an
ongoing flowing conformity and that
dynamical coupling the hebrew word for
it is the off in the bible that
sometimes translated as faith but it
actually means sexual intercourse you
and i don't mean this in a crude fashion
but as opposed to grasping the world in
ego right you can make love with the
world and that's and love is its own way
of knowing that's what I was trying to
talk about I hope that helps in the
expense
ah mark welcome mark always good to see
you I'm insanely dyslexic do you have
pointers for helping me able to follow
this more easily those so afflicted I
don't I don't I know well of course a
bit about dyslexia but I do not know
much about therapies for this I
there are ways of trying to help
obviously that's why I try to give you
the multimodal president it was called
multimodal presentation you know there's
written stuff but there's also spoken
stuff there's also visual stuff to try
and give you mnemonic aids you might
want to try a mnemonic practices instead
of just trying to remember the words see
if you can associate images with the
words and then put the images together
into a small narrative because if you
can talk into imagistic mnemonic rather
than purely linguistic mnemonic the
chances are you'll remember it better so
I mean I know the general strategies are
multimodal and to try and shift onto
Saur imagistic mnemonics mnemonic search
strategies for a memory rather than
purely linguistic but I'm I'm not I'm
not somebody who has expertise in the
therapy of dyslexia those are just
general strategies and perhaps their
help they will help try them out mark
and let me know then go to see you then
thank you
you once said deep meta connects with
grounded being what is that my folks
Petrella T is feeling it as deep quiet
entropy found to people are passed on
and a powerful drive to create to be
yeah that the the ground of being is not
a being it is no thing at all it is Noth
anus are nothingness but not as a
privation of thickness not as a
privation of being a specific object but
instead the actual active power that
affords everything coming into being and
it has aspects there's the way in which
the physical is self-perpetuating and
the vital is self-organizing and the
intelligible is self presencing and the
mystical is self-transcending and all
that self the way is folding around and
expressing itself while participating in
its those for right the the self
continuity of the physical and the
self-organization of the vital and their
self presencing of the intelligible and
the self transcendence of the mystical
they're like four things that are
pointing down you look through them they
you look back through them to that which
affords them it makes them possible
that's what I mean by the ground at the
end and what you're doing in these
practices is coming you can't grasp the
ground of being it's like the Upanishads
said it's not right it's nothing that
you see it is the power by which you see
it is nothing you touch it is the power
by which you touch right so you can't
grasp it this is you can in no way have
the ground of the air it can only you
can only you can only come
- at one mint with it in the pure being
mode you can only be it or that's even a
little too egocentric you can all right
try this without the you there's just
being so I hope that helps so if these
questions are wonderful full of wonder
so thank you so much for joining I want
to thank my dear friend and techno major
Mar and my beloved son Jason who was
again behind the scenes making
everything possible please subscribe to
this channel to be notified in the next
video you'll also find links out there
to the lecture series awakening for the
meaning crisis the discussion that the
alivelu series raises with rob a key
where all of these ideas and themes are
explored more in depth and situated into
a more grounding and enhancing you know
overall finally Oh Sophia the love of
wisdom a way of life invite others who
might benefit by sharing this series you
guys have been wonderfully helpful in
that I ask you to keep doing it please
Brett was here I answered his question
or at least I attempted to and he will
Shepherd you right from this into the
discord server where there are people
there who have done today's session
perhaps we'll go into Lexi Oh Davina
perhaps into via logos there's a
discussion of all of both Awakening and
the meaning Christ as the voices were
baekje you'll find people that I have on
voices with regulate Paul Evander clay
or Rafe Kelley they're there for
discussion it's rich vibrant vital the
link to that is in the description for
this video remember we are doing this
every weekday morning at 9:30 Eastern
Time continuity of practice continuity
of conformity right continuity of
practice is more important than quantity
of process of practice how much you can
grasp
there is no enemy worse than your own
mind and body
there's no friend no ally no true
companion on the path better than your
own mind and body be lamps unto yourself
and to each other
take good care everyone I'll see you on
Monday goodbye